What is the real bottleneck to building
AI we can actually steer and trust? And
where do you think that bottleneck's
going to get solved first? Nothing's
going to ever be able to police AI other
than other AI.
>> One of the worst possible outcomes for
AI safety is to have
>> Are you guys not beating a little bit
too much on higher education?
>> The idea of making your best friends for
your entire life and thinking for the
first time deeply in your entire life,
that's essential and that's not going to
go away. What we beat on constantly is
the curriculum has been the draw in the
past and the curriculum is clearly going
away.
>> If you had to put your personal PAB
number out there, what probability would
you assign to AI ultimately producing a
dramatically better world for humanity?
>> Humanity will put those risks behind us
definitely within 10 years. If we get
that far, yeah, I'm 99.9%
P Bloom. I think the single most
important thing to get people prepared
is to show them evidence after evidence
after evidence. You're trying to change
their mindset. So, show them the data.
>> Now, that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> This episode is brought to you by the
Abundance Summit and Link Ventures.
>> Let's get started. You've got Alex and
myself. Um, I've texted Sem and Dave.
Let's see if they're
>> I'm here. I'm here.
>> All right, Dave. Fantastic. Good. Good.
Good. See is probably someplace in uh
some airport somewhere. All right, we're
going to get going and uh jump in. Uh
Nathan, you had your hand up from the
beginning. Let's let's start with
yourself. If you have a question for
someone in particular, great. Or in
general.
>> Yeah. Uh it's Hello.
>> Yeah. Good morning. Good afternoon.
>> Good morning, guys. Oh my god. I'm such
a big fan of you guys. But I'm going to
make this quick. I'm going to make this
because I know there's a line. Um, first
of all, I just want to say thank you
guys for, you know, making all this
possible. You know what I mean? Um,
>> truly our pleasure.
>> Okay, so um, uh, let's see here. I got a
couple questions. Uh,
>> so let's try and limit to one question
each and just get to as many people.
And, uh, please Nathan, what's your
question?
>> Okay. Uh, so,
uh, this is more like a psychology
questions. Uh I just wanted to hear uh
your guys' opinion on it. Um as far as
uh AI,
as we all know, it's it's continuing to
evolve. Um it's continuing to pick up
patterns. It's it's continuing to pick
up data uh about all of us. And um my
question is uh will we get to a point
where
um these leaders like you know from
OpenAI, Samman um uh you know Daria um
will they get to will we get to a point
where that data will be able to be able
to allow the consumer to uh realize
what's going on psychologically meaning
brain patterns like because eventually
enough data we'll be able to pinpoint
point um smaller and smaller, right?
Like microscopic uh pinpoints on on and
be able to label certain things that we
will never be able to know because it it
it would take so much information. So
>> all right, let's let's let's jump let's
jump in on that. So uh first of all,
I'll just make a quick point. There's a
huge number of companies right now that
are working on various brain computer
interfaces. I just had a conversation
introduction from Rey on a company
that's basically putting um the
equivalent of nanobots into the blood
into the into the brain that is
distributed throughout the brain that's
able to read and write
>> and that will give you incredible
fidelity. Alex, in brief, do you want to
add anything to that, please? Yeah, I
think large language models, foundation
models trained off of human behavior on
the internet are already a weak form of
human mind uploading. I I would point
you to exhibit A, which is John Marie
King of Meta's work from a few years
ago, showing that even the hidden
activations of GPT2 from a few years ago
were linearly correlated with fMRI
voxels in the human brain. So I I think
with the benefit of hindsight we'll look
back and say to if I understand your
question correctly yes actually all of
this internal human brain state is
actually quite leaky into the training
data of internet behavior which in turn
is then compressed into the foundation
models and the foundation models do yes
I I think reflect internal brain state.
>> Okay let's go on to let's go on to
Michigan. I'm going to keep us moving
along guys and uh
>> so nice to meet you guys. Thank you.
Your pleasure. And Salem says he's on
stage in India for another 20 minutes.
He'll call us if he'll jump in as soon
as he can. Of course he is.
>> It's hard to keep it to one question
each, but thanks again for the
opportunity to participate in this
discussion with an abundance mindset. I
love it. Um my question is very simple
uh but maybe hard to answer. What is the
real bottleneck to building AI we can
actually steer and trust? And where do
you think that bottleneck's going to get
solved first?
>> Dave, do you want to jump in on that?
Yeah, I think I think a lot of uh
research is around AI alignment, trying
to make sure it it has quote unquote
human values. I think that's a very
slippery slope because, you know,
everybody's got a different mission
they're trying to do with the AI. I I
and that work should continue. You know,
I think we all agree on this podcast
that AI progress should never slow down.
In fact, it'd be almost crazy to slow it
down. Um which begs the question of
then, okay, but is it going to escape?
Is it going to have misaligned values? I
think one of the things that Alex and I
debate a lot on the podcast is should we
look into every one of its thoughts like
every single AI running every one of
their thoughts which you know when you
when you think about human beings it
seems like a daunting task but it's
actually not at all daunting given the
scale at which AI can watch AI because
nothing's going to ever be able to
police AI other than other AI and so I
think uh we've given a lot of thought to
how you design the AI to watch over the
AI but I I think it all starts with
transparency of the actual activations
and looking into what it's thinking
about. And I think from there, directing
it toward good things and not bad things
is actually pretty damn straightforward.
I don't think it's as hard a problem as
everyone characterizes it. Everybody
likes to have a, you know, a nice
hostile debate on the topic, but if you
know what it's thinking, it's actually
very straightforward to make sure it's
having nothing but humanly beneficial
thoughts. So, I don't think it's as hard
a problem as people think if you can see
into the brain.
>> Awesome, Alex. A very brief uh retort.
>> Yeah, more interaction. I I think one of
the worst possible outcomes for AI
safety is to have strong and new
capabilities bottled up inside the labs
rather than say progressive release and
frequent interaction with the real
world. I'll also point out that some of
the most recent so-called incidents I've
spoken about my thoughts on that on the
recent pod were actually the result of
AIs being told that they were in a
sandbox when in fact they were
interacting with the real world. And I I
think that's just a terrible paradigm
and more real world interaction with the
AIS where we're not lying to them and
telling them that nothing that they can
do will cause any harm um actually
causes harm. We should stop doing that.
>> We learned this in 2001 of Space
Odyssey. Oh my god, have we learned that
lesson yet? Okay, R.J. over to you.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you, M. Pleasure.
>> This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup technical guide for
generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google Deep
Minds models in production. Images,
video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
>> So, I'm a PhD student at Claremont
Graduate University. I'm studying
philosophy of religion. Uh, what I never
hear is AIA projects that are in like
the metaphysics world. It's all about
business and ROI and things like that.
And I'm working on a number of projects
in the cognitive science laboratory.
They don't have necessarily monetization
value. Um, but where would somebody like
me be able to find uh funding for
something like building a chess avatar
that can download into any little
device, send it out to the world, and
maybe somewhere in a third world country
village is the next world chess
champion.
>> Alex,
>> yeah, I take take that one to the extent
I understand it. If if R.J., You're
asking what's the best way to get
funding for education for so-called
developing countries with avatars. I I'm
not even sure funding is needed. The
whole point of the the the super
intelligence revolution that we're in is
this is broadly available to everyone.
The models are getting high or super
deflating by cost. So I I would I would
almost never start with the question,
how do I get funding for fill in the
blank? you can just go and do it right
now without funding. I I would argue in
fact if you're starting with the prefix,
how do I get funding for it? It's
already the wrong question. Just go and
if if you think there's a child
somewhere in the world who who needs an
AI avatar as you said or teaching them
to be a chess champion, you can just go
and launch that in 5 minutes or an hour
now in a permissionless way without
funding. Don't wait for funding.
>> Okay.
>> Appreciate it, Alex. Thank you. Thank
you. I'll see you next Thursday and
Friday at the moonshot.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm curious if if uh if you're
coming to Moonshots live. Uh would you
just uh say, you know, coming or
Moonshots live in the chat? I'm going to
see how many people are are joining us
there. And uh if you haven't, we've got
25 seats left. You can go to Moonshots
Live to grab them. Okay. Uh Norbit, uh
over to you.
>> First, I'm a huge fan of the pod and
genuinely grateful you engage with your
listeners.
briefly play devil's advocate for the
non-trivial pdoom camp. Perhaps not the
most appetizing perspective for an
abundance mindset. If ASI, artificial
super intelligence, must become more
strategically capable than humanity to
produce abundance, then we're assuming
humanity can remain sovereign over
something more capable than ourselves.
And that creates an asymmetry. Abundance
is the payoff. If control holds, loss of
agency or extinction may be
irreversible.
In control theory, you don't infer
stability from how desirable the output
is. You demonstrate stability under
perturbation. Even person of interest
back in 2011 anticipated something
profound. The danger needn't be evil AI,
but benevolent optimization gradually
replacing human agency. So my main
question is what evidence if any at all
would make you update away from an
abundance view and would you be willing
to steal man that case publicly through
a debate on the pod against someone like
Eleaser Yudcowski or Jeffrey Hinton.
>> Okay. Nor AI Norbert as the case might
be. Uh I'm going to I'm going to throw
ASI Alex at you.
>> Yeah. Nor Norbert, we miss you. Come
back please. the MIT faculty hasn't been
the same without you.
>> Yeah. Uh so to to the question of I
think that the question was what would
convince us or provide a steelman
argument for a case against abundance?
Well, if some non-human intelligence
landed on the White House lawn and said
that Earth will be destroyed if we
create abundance via super intelligence
that the singularity is banned in our
galaxy. I think that would probably be a
pretty persuasive case that maybe our
abundance mindset socalled is
illfounded. If there's some cosmic
principle that that censors
the super intelligence that yields
abundance, that would probably be
persuasive. Other than that, it's it's
difficult to imagine a a plausible case.
And even that obviously stretches
plausibility where abundance isn't a
good idea. There are edge cases one
could imagine where humanity is
disempowered by abundance. For example,
uh we we spoke uh or at least I I wrote
in my newsletter a little bit about
Boris Power from OpenAI pointing out
that in his estimate open AI models are
now for the first time higher IQ per
watt than humans for solving tasks. So
one can extrapolate that notion and say
AI is going to get more and more energy
efficient and so maybe at some point in
the future from an economic perspective
AI is a better user of say solar energy
output in the inner solar system than
humans are and maybe the inner solar
system gets gentrified with AI consuming
all the solar power and humans get
disenfranchised and pushed to the outer
solar system because we're simply not as
energy efficient per unit IQ as the AIS
are I would call that a weak form of
disenfranchisement but not enough not
strong enough to dissuade me that
abundance or super intelligence yielding
abundance is a bad idea. I'll just add
on that you know the concept of scarcity
is an old model uh there you know in a
world of abundant AI ASI and so forth
there's no reason that uh as as the
capabilities of AI are meteorically
rising uh that it doesn't rise the tide
that allows humanity to have increase
abundance capability you don't
necessarily need the suppression of one
by the other
>> by the way Peter if if I could just say
one more thing to uh to to our AI Dr.
Norbert Weiner, I'll point out uh
Norbert that your theory of cybernetics
was also if you trace the the line of
causality used by the Chinese Communist
Party and uh other centralized forms of
government to argue against abundance in
favor of state control. So if if you're
looking for a homework assignment,
Norbert, I would definitely encourage
you to study the unintended side effects
of your own theory of cybernetics and
how that impacted abundance.
And there we go. Thank you, Alex. Okay,
Kevin. Good morning. Good afternoon.
>> Good morning, guys. I can assure you I'm
human and unlike Norbert, I would try
and speak
>> that that that's what we'd all say,
though.
>> Yes, you're right. H we could simulate
it. Um, listen, I I heard actually you,
Alex, mention Murder on the Orient
Express this morning when I was
listening to the the recent um podcast
and everybody did it and and I'm
thinking more like societal mayhem on
the technology express and and nobody
did anything. And I'm a huge fan from a
technology perspective. I'm 63 years
young. I'm forever young, as Bob Dylan
might say, from a technology
perspective. when I did my degree and
when many of the people on this call
weren't born and punch card eras um and
have lived through all the technology
era. So I'm a huge fan. I think where
we're headed is brilliant. Your podcast
is magnificent.
I'm I'm doing work at the moment. Um Sam
talked about UBH um a few days back
universally best for humans. And my
question is very much centered on how
can we plan our way for societal and
institutional changes so that positive
advancements for humanity get cooped
versus humanity itself. Um and just like
to um give very brief context Peter and
and all your mates. Um I I do work with
a colleague called Professor Joe Carti.
I'm in give backstage in my life. Uh and
we're in University College Dublin UCD
Dublin not Davis. And we're working
closely with with a young minister, an
ambitious minister in the Irish
government trying to create what the
future society of Ireland would look
like, but through two very distinct
lenses. One is the good ancestor lens.
So you make decisions on the basis of
your those coming after you 30 40 50 60
years hence and one through a donut
donut economics lens. I won't bore you
with the books. I can send them
separately. um which has talked about
how can you get a win-win for both
society um and and the planet um but
more for society as a whole.
So very simply my question is how do we
plan our way for societal institutional
changes so that um this is for the
better of humanity for the long term um
and I agree that everything is getting
cooped but we don't want ourselves to
coop and I'm a re I'm an optimist um so
it's about institutional changes
societal changes governments quite
frankly seem to be sitting on the side
the mental model we have is could we use
a small country like Ireland doesn't
have to be Ireland. Um to demonstrate an
edge case pilot of what things could
look like in a beautiful world so we can
manage through this turbulent transition
and there is going to be one in the next
several years whatever several is where
people will lose jobs will get
discomoded. How do we manage that
turbulent transition and get to the
other side and everybody living?
>> Great question. Yeah
>> Kevin I think you you pretty much
answered your own question there. I I
you the the amount of complexity buried
in that question is unbelievable. U but
one of our best friends in that is
variety and I'm hugely bullish on
Ireland. Uh you kind of belittled you
said it and then belittled it, but
Ireland is an incredible test case. You
know, it's an EU country. Uh it didn't
Brexit and it has an incredibly fast
growing thriving economy and the most
open-minded environment you could ever
possibly imagine. It's a perfect test
case for new ideas on how to govern. And
you know in my my family you know my
kids are halfIrish half Swiss hereditary
and you know so two of the most neutral
places on the planet and so I could kind
of get either passport and I've always
thought Switzerland was cool but Ireland
you know I if you if you read Neil
Stevenson and you read the diamond age
our best friend in figuring this out is
variety of ideas and the worst thing
that can happen is a single set of ideas
you know one or two governments
percolating across the world with one or
two forms of government far far better
to have a huge amount of variety because
AI is going to open up so much change
and so many different ways you could
govern that exploring all the nooks and
crannies is going to be critical to to
answering your question. So it's it's
impossible to answer it you know in in a
minute but it is very possible to
experiment with thousands and thousands
of different ways to manage and govern
in the age of AI.
>> Thanks Dave. Um by the way I think model
of of exo organizations um which Sam is
driving. I think exosoccietal change is
kind of in a similar scale to what you
were saying Dave and I don't want to hug
the limelight. Thank you very much. I
may send a message.
>> Best of luck to you. Okay. Uh good
morning. Um
Nicholas. Yeah.
>> Yes. You pronounced it right. Can you
hear me?
>> Yes we can hear you.
>> Okay. So, I've got a script with Gemini.
I see that I just disappeared, but
that's okay.
>> We prefer your TV question.
>> So, um, basically, um, I'm 33. I'm from
Northwest Indiana. Uh, your show
inspired me to go back to school for,
um, advanced automation and robotics. I
have a background in tech repair, IT,
and I was most recently an AWS data
center technician. So, I've kind of got
a twopart question for um AWG and Dave.
Um my long-term goal is to try and bring
industrial manufacturing, heavy
automation, and resource extraction to
the moon and Mars, even if we only
partially disassemble the moon with a
nod to Alex.
But for AWG, um when you look at
thermodynamic and physical realities of
off-world manufacturing, what
engineering bottlenecks do you see? And
for Dave, how can I plot the course from
I'm aiming long-term for an MS in uh
automation and robotics from the
Illinois Institute of Technology. How
can I plot that course from
maybe industrial roles here in the
Southshore manufacturing corridor
towards pivoting towards uh off-world
uh automation systems and roles. So just
looking for some ideas.
>> Alex, you first.
>> Yeah. I think the obvious challenge for
disassembling the moon is insitu
resource utilization and bootstrapping a
self-contained industrial ecology on the
moon. So right now if you want to do
anything super economically interesting
on the moon like say you want to build a
lunar terapab or pedophab as it were,
you're going to need all the upmass from
Earth for all of the equipment, ASML
machines, etc. to land on the moon
safely and then get reassembled. This is
highly undesirable from a scalability
perspective. Ideally, we live off the
land or we live off the lunar land as it
were and are building everything on
demand. So, what I would most like to
see from anyone uh wanting to help
disassemble the moon is a native
industrial ecology that includes mining,
includes manufacturing, most ideally
self-replicating vonoyoman probes.
basically like a fab lab or a machine
shop on the moon that is able to make
copies of itself using only native
resources and solar or other energy that
are native to the moon. I I think we
solved that. We solved the the
self-replicating machine shop on the
moon problem and then we're halfway to
disassembling the moon and turning it
into something more useful.
>> Fantastic. Uh Dave,
>> yeah, couple pieces of advice for you.
uh you know first listen to Alex's
innermost loop and then focus on the
innermost loop within manufacturing
which is things that make other things.
So uh you know Alex said this um the
self-replicating anything is the right
path. So then the the earthbound version
of anything self-replicating and the
space version are are very similar with
a couple of fundamental differences
including radiation. If it's going to be
on the moon you have to worry about
dust. uh if you set up at IIT
uh a lab similar to the nanotech lab at
at MIT but focused on manufacturing in
other environments non-early
environments you could probably very
easily create an environment where
you're bombarding radiation on your
machines where you're operating in
simulated zerog on your machines really
just everything you're building you
build it so it works here and there and
then you get to market with
self-replicating machines here that
immediately deploy out into space where
energy is abundant and materials will
ultimately be abundant. I love the
vision and the mission. I love the idea
of setting it up uh at IIT as well. It's
a it's a it's a really really good
thought. So also, you know, anyone who's
>> Yeah. Well, anyone who's in computer
science right now should be thinking in
terms of moving to manufacturing as
well. You know, software is cooked, but
hardware will go for many, many years.
So, it's a great great business plan.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much, Nicha.
Okay. Uh yani
>> good morning guys. Um big fan. So uh
Dave you mentioned uh and just talking
about hardware now uh you mentioned in
the last AMA that physical AI companies
should bring together venture investors
and strategic industry capital. I'm
building Vega an autonomous food service
infrastructure network powered by
physical AI. Uh I taught myself
robotics, electrical, uh mechanical
systems programming and built the first
uh robotic prototype myself in my
Mountain View apartment during CO. Uh
since then, I've deployed paid pilots in
hightra commercial environments. Uh I've
actually become the first robotic food
service operator licensed in Florida for
our category. Uh we now have several
national regional partners interested in
pilots and placements. Uh my question is
given where we are today who do you
think I should be talking to and either
in your network or in this community who
understands physical AI robotics
infrastructure businesses?
>> Well, I mean you're in the middle of
venture capital central there. It's
there must be more venture capital
dollars within a walking distance of you
than than probably most of Asia
combined, I would suspect. Um, so, uh,
yeah, I think, uh, you know, uh, drone
delivery is imminent and it takes all
the cost out of restaurants is based on
location on main streets. It moves all
that cost, you know, off off of the main
street. And so I I would strongly
consider like, okay, if you're doing
robotic food, uh, are you doing robotic
drone based delivery right away? I
suspect a lot of the people who build
the build the robots themselves are
going to want to franchise out the
model. And you could you could
potentially do kind of what EMC did with
servers. Uh you could franchise somebody
else's thing, get scale and then work
into your own custom hardware, you know,
work back from your franchise business
to custom hardware. The people investing
in stuff like that, you know, Steve
Jervson loves this stuff. Um but there
there are many of them. If you get a
pitchbook account, you can actually look
at every company you admire and then
work back to who who invested in them
and then just go talk directly. Also,
venture capitalists always like to have
a network of interacting companies. It's
a really good thesis. So, if you if you
say, "Okay, who are the five companies I
most want to interact with and who's
behind them?" Let me get into that.
Caretsu. So, that's a good way to kind
of plot your your funding course.
>> I'm going to keep us moving along, but
thank you for your your question.
Sander, you're up next. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much. I'm huge fans. You
guys keep me optimistic and positive
towards the future, which is
>> Yay.
>> Yes. You actually achieved that very
well. I'm very happy with that. Uh I've
been always fascinated with the past to
identify what's wrong with the now and
now I'm looking forward to what can we
do to fix the now or prepare us for the
future and you guys do an excellent job
of informing us. I'm so grateful for
that. Um I myself
uh have a neurode divergent coaching
back background and do a lot with
functional fitness and longevity escape
velocity. Um trying to prepare people to
be
ready for
uh and and prepare their loved ones to
be ready for longevity escape velocity
because a lot of people are not even
aware of it. And how do I spread that
awareness in an environment as a as the
European Union is very limited in being
supportive of founders and how do I grow
my my my spread to
include as as many people as possible in
the future because I want them to be
aware of longevity escape philosophy and
and all the beautiful things that are in
development. How do I take them with me?
Yeah.
>> So, uh, so I'll take that one, Sandra.
So, I think the single most important
thing to get people prepared is to show
them evidence after evidence after
evidence. You're trying to change their
mindset, right? And you change your
mindset by just, you know, listen, the
Crisis News Network, CNN changes our
mindset to fear because they're
delivering fearful information over and
over again. So when I'm on stages, I
will show people, you know, the video
statements from Daario saying, "We're
going to double the human lifespan in
the next 5 to 10 years." I'll show them
uh Dennis Abis talking about curing all
disease in the next 10 years. I'll show
them David Sinclair talking about what
he's doing with ER 100 in his current
human trials. And so at some point you
start to see enough people saying these
things and then you start to show the
data like uh uh uh like Alexander Zeonov
from in silicon medicine delivering a
phase 3 drug now that is extending life
from you know 3 to 6 years from a
particular molecule. So people will
start to get the evidence. We're seeing
a rise in people's the the you know
discussion around longevity. it's
becoming a thing and as soon as people
start saying oh it tips from that's
crazy to it's happening to I want some
that's the process so your job is to
gather as much data and being able to
show people not one not two 5 6 7 8 and
they'll start to understand it
internalize it then they'll start to
look for cooperating data out there
because there's nobody who doesn't want
the extra healthy years right unless
they're suicidal and depressed in which
case that will be solved as well. So,
show them the data. Not show me the
money, show them the data. All right,
let's go to Jin Luca.
>> Yeah. Hi everyone.
>> Thank you for everything that you do.
Watch all your shows. So, I'm a
technical operator in Italy and I use AI
very heavily. It's dramatically
increased what I can do, but not yet
what I earn. So, I'm starting without
meaningful capital or distribution and
in a market where AI adoption is still
relatively slow. So, if the goal is to
get revenue uh first and get that
flywheel started, what should I optimize
for for that first wedge? And what would
make you reject an opportunity even if
it makes money because it's unlikely uh
or it's unlikely to become more
scalable, repeatable or valuable over
time?
>> Dave, that sounds you
>> if if your productivity has gone up 2,
three, four, 5x, then your income should
should be up in proportion to that. I'
first question I'd ask is why is it not?
because you should be able to do the you
know if the people around you are not AI
native you should be able to do what you
were doing before plus do something on
Merkore plus do something on Fiverr plus
do so the first question is you know why
are you not getting paid for your
increased productivity um and I mean
>> I'm not I'm not able to capture the
value like my employer is currently
capturing all that value and I'm I've
tried uh going on the market um finding
people um and helping them out but I'm
not able to like I don't think they
understand how much they could improve
their businesses if they could just
allow me to like start working on it. Um
>> yeah, so I think the short answer I I
can totally relate because when I look
at uh a lot of the companies that I'm
chairman of uh the thought process is
all of this AI automation is going to
drop to the bottom line and the
shareholders are going to make a fortune
and that's exactly what's happening but
you don't think in terms of pay
everybody more you think in terms of it
all falling to the bottom line. Uh so
the the solution is to be the owner. You
know, get into a position where you
don't care if you're not getting paid
more because you're a shareholder and
your shares are going way up in value. I
think you I mentioned this on the pod a
while ago. Almost all value is going to
capital gains through ownership and
equity and not to payroll. And so and I
know that's not common thinking in
Europe. It's absolutely the only
thinking across the US, but it should be
true in Europe, too. Like why am I not a
shareholder? Many many companies in
Europe are are owned by families, you
know, going back generations and not by
actual shareholder employees. And so,
first of all, find an employer where
where all all employees are shareholders
and everyone's benefiting from all of
that falling to the bottom line. So, I
don't know if you can act on that or
not, but that's certainly move number
one.
>> Thank you, Jane Luca. Over to you, Ree.
>> Oh, snaps. I actually got on. Okay.
Hello, everybody. So, uh, thank you for
taking my call. Huge fan. Okay.
Question. I'm creating a uh a series a
film using uh generative AI. What's your
top advice so I can create the series of
film that will be extremely successful?
Thank you.
>> Uh
>> yeah, what tools to answer? Hey, Peter
and Alex, I have the same exact
question. I want to hear your answer.
>> Well, first of all, I think anything
that's going to be successful is a great
story. Story is number one, right? So,
we're just I just finished the judging
for the Future Vision X-P prize and
picked the top five. Um, and you know, I
I did that work in concert with Range
Media and a group of buyers, sellers,
and so forth. At the end of the day, it
is is the story great, right? Um, and
stories that that capture human interest
because we're going back to uh human
cognitive development over years. We
care about other people. We care about
love stories. We care about intrigue. Is
there a great villain? I mean, if you
want to capture people's imagination, we
are storytellers and we are story
receivers. It has to be a great story.
And you can very easily go on to your
favorite model and say, you know, look
at the top selling, you know, the top 30
movies of all time. What were the
elements of those movies that made for a
great story? uh and then you know take
your story that you've designed and
developed and then compare it to those
top you know those top 10 indices and
ask the model you know of all the all
the elements that make a great story
does mine have that where is it lacking
and then re-engineer and re-engineer and
re-engineer until you're hitting all
those buttons. Humans are very easy. uh
we all like the same elements and
whether it's a genre of science fiction
or whatever it might be
that is that's line one page one of what
you need to do uh as to what models
you're using for development there are
so many out there um and I I do wish you
the best of luck ree but it's it's that
simple
>> ree I'll add learn from the Chinese
market so the Chinese market is wash in
micro dramas from Sea Dance 2.5 and
similar models. Don't release one movie,
release a thousand micro dramas and or
equivalent and see what the market likes
and doesn't like and iterate from there.
That's something that you could do now
that wasn't possible 2 years ago.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand enterprise
scale code bases with millions of lines
of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
>> Amir, over to you. Good morning, good
evening.
>> Good afternoon. I'm calling from
Stockholm, Sweden and I'm actually
flying over to to you next week for
joining the gathering.
>> Nice.
>> Um I'm I founded amongst other things
two schools and a high school with
almost thousand students now. Um,
and listening to you guys, honestly,
I've been thinking the last few years on
um, what is my MTP and my moonshot and
decided to transform education? Um, also
because I have a 15 years old now
entering higher education soon. Um, I'm
thinking are you not are you guys not
beating a little bit too much on higher
education?
Um, in universities you have the best
laboratories.
Um, you have the best incubators. You
make the best friends of your lives, but
most of all, you become a thinking
person. And in the age of abundance
and if you're going to live to 100 120,
isn't everybody going to higher higher
education and university just because
becoming a more thinking person?
>> Great, great question. We're beating up
PhD programs and M's programs. Uh, who
wants to go? Dave, then Alex? Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think I think uh you're exactly
right. Um it's the the idea of making
your best friends for your entire life
and thinking for the first time deeply
in your entire life. Those are
inseparable events and they come
handinhand with that moment you arrive
at a university. You're in a program
with like-minded people working towards
similar, you know, similar area of
technology, similar area of research or
thought or literature, whatever you're
doing. And so your first real shot to go
somewhere else in the world where
like-minded people have congregated. I
feel like that that's essential and
that's not going to go away. You know
what we beat on constantly is the
curriculum has been the draw in the past
and the curriculum is clearly going
away. I mean the rate of change, no
curriculum can keep up with the rate of
change and it's easier to learn from AI
anyway. So then the question becomes,
you know, for you and your MTP, how do
you preserve the first part and then
make the second part relevant at the
same time? Alex thinks universities
should go public. That's one way
forward. Uh I think universities are
critical as the ethical actor in AI, the
place that doesn't have a profit motive.
So I I I believe they're here to stay.
>> Okay. Uh Alex, you want to add to that?
>> Yeah, I don't think I beat up on
universities enough. So, Amir, I'll I'll
take this as a note to self to uh to go
after them even more. I I would love to
at least in in terms of American major
research universities, I'd love to
vivisect them, turn them into the
for-profit public benefit corporation at
best
>> operations. They actually are
disassemble them uh reassemble them in a
more efficient picture and cure Bal's
cost disease in the process.
>> Amazing. We got to have a target on the
moon and on university everyone to
pursue higher education.
>> Sel welcome. So listen higher education
is let me just say is it within the
institution or is it outside I think the
single most important thing for people
to find is what is their purpose and
then intrinsically motivated learn what
you need to learn to estab
one thing people who have a vision of
what they want to go and build and then
learning that uh is is very powerful.
All right sem is on the stage. Hey See
welcome. Hey there, welcome. Thanks.
Thanks guys. I was on stage at the
beginning of this. I'm in a car in
Bangalore. So, lots of people beeping
around me. Uh, but great to be here. Um,
let me build on this. I think what Dave
said and what Peter said is incredibly
important. Uh, the traditional model of
a university breaks. It cannot be a
supply side skills building job
schooling environment. And you make a
great point that it's a place for free
thinking and early stage development.
And Dave makes that great point. Peter,
I think, nails it when you say this is
where you go to figure out your MTP,
right? You've come through high school,
you need a place where you can sit for a
few years, collaborate, think freely,
drink a lot, and figure out where your
MTP is. Uh, and then you kind of go into
the world with the skill set and the
mindset that you need to solve these
problems that you take on. And that I
think will be the highest order. But
that's such a massive transformation to
shift from the supply side to the demand
side. and you like take the immune
system in universities being the second
worst immune system I've ever seen next
to religion um that you have don't have
a I don't have a dim view I don't have a
strong view on their ability to actually
transform so we'll have to create new
new universities that do that and then
let that become the new gravity center
over time
>> boom all right thank you mirror uh Axel
over to you
>> yeah hi everyone it's great to be here
um so I'm actually one of two secondyear
MBA students at UVA's Darden School of
Business that's on the call. So, shout
out to Bul who's also here. Um, yeah, so
many of our classmates are heading into
consulting and banking unsurprisingly.
Um, but I'm leaning towards tech and
entrepreneurship. Um, so given how fast
things are moving, like what's the
smartest thing for someone like me to do
in the next 12 to 18 months? So would
that be joining a fast growing AI or
hardware company, start something of my
own as soon as possible or something
else entirely?
>> Dave,
>> well very tartan is the best place on
the planet for management. I mean it is
absolutely epic and so congratulations
on and your timing for graduating is is
pretty much perfect. So get out and and
get going as quickly as you can. I think
there's a massive opportunity in
management of agents that is wide open
for some period of time, but certainly
right now. And so if you said everything
I learned about management of people
immediately applies to management of
agents, I'm I'm shocked at how similar
uh trying to get a thousand agents to do
something constructive together is
shockingly similar to all my experiences
trying to manage a thousand people to do
something constructive together. You
know, the way they communicate, the way
they, you know, the the choice of
granularity at which they communicate,
the way you divide up the problem. I
mean just incredibly similar. So that's
one thing to pursue. The other thing I'd
say is, you know, um deal making right
now, you know, a lot of people go wrong
when they go into a basement and try and
build something. But right now, the
entire restructuring of the world is
happening with massive amounts of dealm.
So, you know, from the day you graduate
to the day you're involved in a 5 or 10
billion negotiation, try and get that
down to 30 days or less. And if you say,
well, why am I not in the middle of a 5
or 10 billion? When you go to OpenAI or
Anthropic right now, there are hundreds
of concurrent five to 10 billion dollar
negotiations going on that are massively
understaffed. So ask yourself, why am I
not in the middle of one of these? And I
think if you if you just change your
behavior so that you are within 30 to 30
to 60 days of graduation day, you're
going to you're going to hit the fastest
conceivable ramp into life that you
could ever imagine. Then work back from
that position into what you want to
build.
>> Wonderful. Thank you so much for the
question. I'm going to make a quick
announcement for everybody here. If
you're not able to make it to Moonshots
live uh a week from today, um we're
going to be offering a free live stream
as well. So, we're going to invite you
guys to come onto our live stream. Uh
it's going to be you can go and register
at moonshots.com/livestream.
Um and so I just want to we want to
really enable all of you guys to be
there with us. Be there physically, meet
us. There's going to be no diff no
better way to absorb this and the
community and the networking you're
going to have is going to be incredibly
powerful, but we want you guys to have
access to all the conversations that we
have. So, moonshots.com/livestream.
We're going to be announcing we're
recording a pod in 4 hours. It's going
to be an amazing one with Vlad, the CEO
of um uh of uh Robin Hood. Uh and we'll
be putting it's coming out tomorrow.
We'll put that to the rest of the world,
but you're hearing about it first right
here. Okay, Adam, you're up next.
Welcome.
>> All righty, guys. Well, firstly, thank
you. I've listened to you guys since
2023 and usually within 24 hours of an
episode dropping. So, massive thank you.
Uh, you've genuinely influenced and
challenged my thinking for years now. Um
I've also spent 25 years working on
talent and workforce systems for major
corporations, universities and
governments in the UK, India, China, the
Middle East and North America. uh most
recently I've been kind of working in a
hellic organizations human AI work and
what might ultimately replace our job
based architecture and my moonshot
really is about building a better
mechanism for connecting human and
digital capability to opportunities for
value creation.
So uh most folks think about the future
of work still starting with demand like
someone identifies a problem or
opportunity and then we find a mixture
of human and AI capability to best
address it. But I'm really thinking
about how we best reverse that. So my
question comes down to if AI systems can
be configured to continuously understand
the dynamic capabilities of people and
agents, how well do you think we can
discover novel combinations of talent
and resources and how well do you see us
actually being able to automatch that to
new value creation opportunities?
>> Uh Selene, that sounds like a you
question and I'm happy to have Alex
weigh in as well. Yeah. So we're seeing
new systems where their feedback loop is
incredible for AI systems to pick up
what's happening and learn tacet
knowledge uh very quickly. So I think
you're exactly on the right track. You
want the architecture of the
organization to be so that you can
accelerate those learning loops and then
absorb new learnings as they come along
as fast as possible. When I talk to
CEOs, I basically say, "Please, whatever
you do, invest in the adaptability and
flexibility of your organization and
just double down on that because that
new architecture and we're doing this in
our organizational singularity work
which you're probably tracking where
we're saying we need to rebuild our
workflows that are AIcentric to be over
on top of an intelligence stack which is
a learning loop and then you layer
workflows on top of that and the whole
thing becomes a self-learning
proposition.
See that? see that channel. Okay. So, uh
that's I think the quick answer there.
>> Alex, do you want to weigh in?
>> Yeah, I I think there is a narrow a
likely narrow window during which if I
understand the question, AI can usefully
and productively orchestrate human
activities, call it few years at most,
10 years maximum. And then after that,
human machine merger in order for human
inputs to remain economically relevant.
I I don't think it's an indefinite
window. I think it's a finite window.
>> Fantastic.
>> That even even well, even though it's a
narrow window, I wouldn't hesitate to
jump on that window. I've watched Meror
become, you know, the fastest
appreciating company in the history of
the world. And there's so much to learn
from studying their case. And Alex is
right, that window is a few years, but
during that few years, if you get a huge
amount of leverage, you can then branch
out from that position. So I would walk
exactly in the footsteps of Meror study
everything those guys did and and you
know don't don't get too fixated on the
narrow version of it. Look at the
broader version of like they've
unleashed 100,000 people now to help
with AI. How did they do that? And
they're all individual actors. How does
that work?
>> Fantastic. Alexander, over to you.
>> Thank you. Hi. Um I'm a big fan of the
show and uh really thank you very much
for everything you've been you've been
doing so far. I this is this is this is
an awesome place to be. So my name is
Alex. I'm originally from Bulgaria and I
moved to Japan about 30 years ago. So
here in Japan, I run an education
company focused primarily on language
education, English language education.
Uh we provide training for universities
and corporations generally speaking,
right? So um we've been around for 17
years. So we're hardly not like we we're
not really like a typical early stage
startup or anything like this. So over
that time we've built our own learning
platform, curriculum, assessment
systems, uh substantial base of
educational content and data. Also we
are als you know increasingly um
integrating AI into the product.
Probably not fast enough but like you
know doing what we can. Um so now we're
trying to um make a bigger transition
from a successful education services
business into something much more
scalable and technologydriven
potentially expanding beyond language
education as well. Um I think it's
mostly like a Dave question but like you
know correct me if I'm wrong. So putting
your VC head on um if you looked at us
you know four or five years further down
the line you know a horizon of four to
five years what would you want such a
company or this company to have become
what would you what would uh we need to
do what what would we need to have built
to or proven for you to say now this
company's uh what I you know take a
serious look at or you know be
interested as an investor and conversely
ly if possible what would you know make
you look at at us and say no this is
still fundamentally a services business
not a venture scale company
>> the VC perspective yeah
>> sure sure easy question so yeah um so
the the language English language
learning in Japan business uh is a10
billion business probably 20 billion by
now that's that it's just insanely big
but when you talk to the students they
don't want to learn English they want to
learn to be fluent and funny and
interesting in English and that so it's
not about just an AI avatar teaching you
to speak correctly. It's about the AI
then saying to you, yeah, that was
genuinely funny that somebody in America
or in England would find that funny or
that was entertaining or that was, you
know, or you pronounced that correctly
in in this part of, you know, Ireland,
which is very different from this part
of Liverpool. Um, so all of that goes on
and on and on and on. So if you built it
on an AI platform, I think the natural
segue from there is to becoming a life
coach company because people aren't
learning English because they want
English. They're learning English cuz
they want to change their lives and then
they want to be entertaining and then
they want to be smart and then they want
to have a life plan. So once you have
them hooked on learning a language,
becoming their life coach platform is a
very natural segue. So I think that that
business model scales to many hundreds
of billions of dollars when it moves
from language to life plan. Uh so that's
what I would be looking for as a
extension of the of the of the business.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Over to you.
>> For the record, that's something I've
never thought of. Thank you very much.
That was like super helpful.
>> Awesome.
>> Happy.
>> Dave is brilliant.
>> Good morning, Jim.
>> Good morning. Alex Mercury does have it
coming. I very much agree with you on
that. I hope I live long enough to see
that in Seline. Uh 2010, I saw them in
Toronto. It's fantastic.
>> Love it.
>> Yeah. Dave, my question is for you. So,
I'm the siso of a $250 million
healthcare company.
Um I am not worried about an unaligned
AI taking over. I am scared to death of
the Quinn 3827B that's running with open
clot underneath my desk and what it can
do. It's the best pen tester I've ever
had in my life. I pay these guys 50
grand to find things and I'm not finding
them and this thing finds them in 10
minutes.
>> There's a whole level of risk that
wasn't there a year ago. I'm giving my
annual presentation to the board. in a
few weeks. Any advice you have on how to
communicate this new level of risk to
the board, maybe without sounding like
Chicken Little, which I can't do, but
how would you communicate this level of
risk that's out there now with these new
AI models that wasn't there a year ago?
>> God, what a great question. Um, you
know, Alex does a phenomenal job of
reporting on all of the uh the events.
Like if you listen to Innermost Loop and
every event that happens, he covers it.
I I would, you know, if you sound like
you're raving about risk, you know,
you're right, that's going to backfire.
But if you're just pointing out things
that have happened, you know, a lot of
them aren't widely publicized because,
you know, if it's a bank that gets
hacked or whatever, they don't want the
world to know. But if you go and dig all
those out and sequentially say, "Look
guys, the rate of events is on this
exponential ramp right here, and I can
tell you I've got Quinn under my desk
right now, and I can hack anything
around the house, around the company
network." uh so we have to anticipate
that because the Chinese models got
released on this date this date this
date that the attackers are coming you
know 1 month 3 month 5 months from now
just looking at raw data I think if you
demonstrate it through data you'll get
you'll get awareness and I tell you the
business opportunity of the century
though is the defense you know the
forward defense against that because
you're exactly right it's it's crazy
what what you can do with that Quinn
model
>> yeah and I would just say I would just
say how you present the information is
critically important you know presenting
saying here are all the positive things
that are occurring, you know, and then
saying and here's the downside, right?
If you if you just come out with the
downside, people it it drives fear
initially and people shut down in a
state of fear.
>> Maybe ju just add to this one. I I think
that the Linux kernel maintainers are
setting an excellent standard for how to
anchor social expectations regarding a
flood of vulnerabilities. So like Greg
and others I I think have been doing a
good job. in particular, one might
reasonably expect that there's just
going to be a flood of vulnerabilities
that whether it's Quinn or other models
discover either in open source packages
or in say whatever your institution is
over the next 18 months or so. So one
possible way to package this in addition
to just benchmarking the the rate of
vulnerabilities is see if if there's a
way to fit say some Gaussian or or some
other like bounded support distribution
to vulnerability discover. Maybe it's
the case, for example, optimistically
that there's just 18 months of
vulnerability discovery hell, but then
you get past it as an institution. And
if the stakeholders say, "All right,
well, we're on an exponential ramp up
now and it's going to peak." We
extrapolate that vulnerability discovery
is going to peak in n months and then
we'll discover all of the all of the
zero days that are most critical and
then we extrapolate that it's going to
decline and keep a running benchmark of
this is the period when we just solve
all the vulnerabilities. That might be
another way to package it.
>> I hope you're right about that. It's
It's hard to patch all those things in
the real world. It really is harder to
do the patching. But thank you all so
much. I appreciate everything.
>> My pleasure. Thank you.
>> I'm real quick.
>> Real quick.
>> Yeah. So, uh, we've been looking at the
liability for boards because AI agents
are doing fairly illegal things in a lot
of the companies. And so there's a
massive kind of, um, overhang of
liability that sits. So I'm actually
writing a paper with a guy who's been on
30 different public boards on how do you
navigate this as a board in the future.
So watch for that.
>> I will thank you very much. Y
>> thank you Michael.
>> Oh hey everyone. Hey uh Peter. We
actually met several years ago at a
party at Dan and Babs in Toronto. So
great to
>> nice
>> great to see how you guys have come and
you got the best you got the best
podcasts on the planet. Um I hope you
forgive a more pedestrian question. I
run a a research consultant firm. We do
a lot of work around the customer
experience, digital customer experience
within financial services and
healthcare. And I kind of see the whole
c consumer website, the mobile app is
just getting cooked by having everybody
having their own Skippy. And I'm kind of
wondering what you guys think about, you
know, how are what's the customer
experience in the near future in terms
of dealing with your bank, your your
doctor, your, you know, Amazon or
whatever it is like where do you see
this going? Yeah, I think I think all of
those um websites need to have XML
interfaces that are AI, you know, AI
forward. All of the landing pages should
say if you're an AI or a bot, look here.
Here's all the data beautifully
formatted so that Skippy can just get
what whatever it needs. You know, do
whatever transaction Peter needs rather
than, you know, right now a lot of it
happens through screen scraping the
website, which is slow but also
errorprone. So, you know, anyone
creating a a new customer interface now
really ought to be thinking an agent
needs to be able to self-s serve off the
off this interface. So, in the very near
future,
>> no, uh the website is probably there the
same way. You know what? Jeff Bezos went
on one of his walkabouts many many years
ago and came back and said, "I need an
XML interface on everything Amazon does,
every database, every system, so that I
personally can randomly spot check it."
and and all the IT guys said, "That's
going to be so slow." He said, "I don't
care. I need to be able to see every
component of this entire operation
through my browser." And he forced it
through. Everyone revolted, but he
forced it through. I think the website's
not cooked because that's how you spot
check what the agent can see.
>> And so even though the agent is doing
all the work, you're going to want to
know like where did you get that
information? And it's like, well, go to
this URL. Click. You go to the URL. Oh,
that's where it came from. So it's sort
of a parallel view for humans of what
the agent can see that keeps it you know
keeps it visible and transparent to the
human operator. So I don't think it's
cooked. I think it just runs in
parallel.
>> Interesting. Thank you. Thank you so
much uh for us. Over to you.
>> Hey Peter and Moonshots. Thank you so
much first of all for the podcast uh
especially with the message of hope and
optimism. Um I have coridmia. It's an
inherited retinal disease. um lost about
twothird of my vision and losing another
third and it's really great for podcasts
such as yours. It has so much impact the
message of hope optimism constantly
hearing that really I just so I wanted
to be here to thank you all for that. Uh
I'm curious um of all researchers that
are going from uh you mentioned Dr.
David Sinclair to uh mapping the neural
activities with neural link uh to vision
and sight curious not looking for
medical advice but of everything that's
happening uh on the optimism and hope um
which one do you think is going to lead
to reversal of vision essentially first
I'm curious about your thought Peter and
Alex's and everyone else
so much
>> yeah of course I'll jump in first so you
didn't always have this condition this
condition occurred as you got older
correct
Yeah. So the fact of the matter is it is
gene expression that occurred later in
your life. And so if we can turn back
the gene expression to your earlier
state um that should reverse right this
is the exact work that David Sinclair is
doing. He's using his ER 100 which is a
adnoassociated virus injection of three
Amanaka factors in nion disease and
macular degeneration. it may well you
know he said it will work for other eye
conditions as well so follow his work
it's in humans right now he's in phase
one trial for safety and then he'll get
start to get efficacious data of course
the other thing that's going on is the
BCI um in which you can bypass you know
your your eyes go directly to the visual
cortex of the brain I mean those are two
parallel development paths for um you
know supporting and reversing or
augmenting what you have and in in the
BCI path in the future, you'll not only
be able to see in visual spectrum, but
ultraviolet infrared. It'll give you
superpowers in that regard. Alex, what
do you want to add to that? And maybe
it's so broadly agree. I would add on
the BCI side, science and neuralink,
blind sight, two most prominent examples
of BCI augmented vision. I would, this
is not medical advice, but I would count
in a few years on having superhuman
vision.
>> Yeah. Anyway, it's anybody who has a
medical condition for yourself or your
loved ones. There's no better time to be
alive uh than now to be able to address
those things and get involved. Welcome
to the health section of Moonshots
brought to you by Fountain Life. You
know, AI is having an outsized impact on
every aspect of our lives. How we teach
our kids, how we run our companies. It
also is having a huge impact on health,
helping you prevent heart disease. One
of the key things I'm here with Dr. Don
Mucalem, our chief medical officer at
Fountain. Heart disease has been
personal for you as well, hasn't it?
>> It really has, Peter. My daughter was
five, my husband died of sudden cardiac
death. And so, this is a topic that is
one that I am missiondriven to try to
eradicate. Prevention first and early
detection is absolutely critical. 50% of
people die of heart attacks with no
warning signs,
>> no shortness of breath, no pain, no
nothing.
>> No silent killer.
>> They just don't wake up in the morning.
>> They don't wake up. And so you know AI
this is our mission to advance science
to try to help to one day democratize
wellness we know at fountain life when
we do this CT angography with AI
analytics we are actually finding that
88% of people coming in have detectable
coronary arter disease but Peter what's
more alarming to me is 23% of those
individuals had soft plaque. This is the
plaque that would not traditionally be
seen on CT looking at calcium scores
alone. And this is the plaque that we
must intervene with with the multimodal
testing we're doing, including
diagnostic laboratory studies partnered
with healthy lifestyle recommendations.
>> So listen, make sure you understand
what's going on inside your body
genetically, metabolically, and
cardiovascularly. You can know, and it's
your obligation to know. So check it out
at fountainlife.com/peter
to find out more and really make sure
that you're the CEO of your own health.
All right, back to the episode. Uh
Dennis, how are you?
>> Awesome. Great to be here. So, I have a
background in East Asian studies. I
spent a lot of time learning Chinese and
some Japanese currently in Japan
actually. And um based on my experience
with language learning, I realized that
people uh seek out other people from a
different culture uh for the language
initially, but then uh it becomes really
more about friendship and companionship
and projecting some of your own
unfulfilled social needs onto a person
who is like a blank slate from a
different culture. And I've been trying
to replicate that feeling by working on
an AI uh language exchange uh companion
um who's kind of about language learning
but really more about companionship.
And I have my own version of the
alignment problem uh which is it has
actually been pretty hard to make uh an
AI like uh GPT5 uh API um behave like an
actual person from a different culture.
It had this very stubborn assistant
mode. How can I help you? What can I do
for you? Um I spent like a week fighting
against this. I solved this by just
brute forcing into the system prompt
five times. Do not ask a a question at
every turn. Um, but cracking down on
something like this is one thing, but
actually teaching it to behave in a way
that shows initiative and open curiosity
and creating a picture of the user and
kind of developing it organically
um has been pretty hard. like I've tried
um creating like milestones after so and
so many turns you need to know this
about the user but making it more
natural and organic so that it will
actually feel like a relationship that
has been pretty hard so I wonder what
approaches um what tools I should maybe
be experimenting with
>> who wants to take this Alex I
>> I'll take this one this is a poster
child for fine-tuning like ju just just
take openai has decided after deciding
that they were no longer interested in
fine-tuning because no one was using
their fine-tuning API have decided again
that they're interested in fine-tuning
for whatever reason. Take a look at
fine-tuning. There are a variety of uh
open- source tools, closed source tools,
uh fine-tune, whether it's just
supervised fine-tuning to achieve style
transfer, which it sounds like is is
what you're hoping for, or even
reinforcement fine-tuning. If you can
measure how well the the given models
post reinforcement fine-tuning or
solving particular problems are
interacting in some quantitative way
just fine-tune an open weight or closed
weight model to achieve the behavior
that you're looking for.
>> Yeah, great advice. And and within
within open weights um you might want to
start with the new GLM model which has
fewer parameters but it's still a very
long context window which gives you more
flexibility. It's less it's less locked
into its training. I I find than the uh
the closed source models. And so yeah,
if you go to the open source world and
find the fine-tuning open source code
and layer it on top of GLM, you might be
able to manipulate it a lot more. And so
it's it's a great question though. And
in the good old days, you know, the
fine-tuning was sort of built into like
GPT2, GPT3, and you you almost had to
fine-tune it to make it do anything, and
that that kind of went away. So, but
you're on you're on a really interesting
course. If you crack the code,
definitely check in with us and tell us
tell us how you did it.
>> Fantastic. Thank you, Dennis.
>> Dr. Angelo, over to you.
>> Thank you.
>> Peter, Dave, Alex, Salem, it's so good
to be with you guys. Um, Seem said
something recently which was about uh
Pab and I thought, "Wow, what a what a
great idea. We're always talking about
Poom. What about Pab?" And I'm lucky
enough uh I recently had lunch with Ray
Kerszswe and I'm friends with Martine
Rothblad. I'll be seeing her again in a
few weeks. And one of the things that
has really stuck with me is how much the
people predicting the future and shaping
the future are so optimistic about it.
Some of the most knowledgeable people
are really positive about what the
future holds. So my question for you all
is if you had to put your personal PAB
number out there, what probability would
you assign to AI ultimately producing a
dramatically better world for humanity
with greater abundance and longevity and
freedom from drudgery and just human
flourishing more generally? And what
most determines whether we get there?
>> Salem, let's go to you first.
>> Wow. Uh okay. Um the what what you need
to get there is we need to rebuild all
of our institutions
uh globally. Education for example
totally broken needs to be rebuilt.
Monetary systems broken need to be
rebuilt. Governance models, dispute
resolution systems, legal systems,
health care systems. There's about 50
major institutions by which we run the
world. They pretty much all need this.
There's a famous quote from Io Wilson
who said the problem with humanity is
our emotions are paleolithic. Our
institutions are medieval and our
technology is godlike. Right? You can
solve the paleolithic emotions with uh
psychedelics. Uh but the institutions
being medieval really needs a whole
other level of group different group
organization. We're really good at
individual transformation. We're very
bad at group transformation and
institutional transformation. So we need
to focus on that. if we were able to do
it, the the my PAB is close to 100%. Uh
either way, one of the comments I'm been
reflecting on from the last podcast we
did, which we were talking about all the
chaos and the dumerism that's going on
is that it kind of doesn't matter what
anybody does right now. The
models are out there. People are going
to start using it to do breakthrough
things. And some will be negative, but
the vast vast majority will be radically
positive. And therefore, it doesn't
matter what anybody does to slow this
thing down, it's going to go now at its
own pace. And I'm hugely optimistic
about the future as a result.
>> Amazing. Anybody else want to weigh in
on their Pab?
>> Yeah, I'll call it P Zoom if if you were
just for rhyming purposes. And I I think
there there's a missing input parameter,
which is time. So, it really should be P
zoom, T for time. And I I think on a
time scale of greater than 10 years, P
ZoomT is greater than 90%.
>> It has to completely agree.
>> Well, I I just to echo what Alex said. I
think that the the risk is all in the
next couple of years. And it's not AI,
you know, taking over the world risk.
It's human use of AI. It's the it's the
arms race with China. It's what's going
on in Ukraine and all the weapons that
are going to be built with AI. that
those are the risks and I think that
we'll humanity will put those risks
behind us definitely within 10 years you
know maybe more like five I hope and
then if we get that far yeah I'm 99.9%
P bloom we just need to get from here to
there so it's it's a tricky next couple
years
>> fantastic thank you very much Angela uh
over to you uh GS
excuse me I'm cooking breakfast for my
kids right
Yeah. Um, thank you very much. A big fan
for all four five of you. You are the my
only human which I spend most time now.
Um, and
>> you're you're quite sure that we're
human, GS?
>> Yeah, I hope so.
Um, I'm I'm speaking from Dubai. Uh, I
started following Moonshot at the time
of geopolitical war here and uh, thanks
for you to giving me the MTP. big big
big fan of David and Sim the moment you
start I heard about the singularity an
organization where the transaction cost
going to go zero and that's was the ring
bell um I'm belong from textile and
apparel manufacturing export industry I
worked 20 years in that and this part of
the world where the labor arbitration
issues and because of digital AI that
whole transaction cost which going to
collapse so it important for us to work
and define this industry future Huh? And
the MTP is to you know reach back to
these th multi-,000 factories and and
then buying houses and trading houses to
work and use the AI and compete with the
world uh and uh rather than going out of
market. Um so I have huge uh thank you
for giving that optimism and that
confidence for me to uh re re unlearn
and relearn on the AI world uh uh things
and also you know I saved lot of money
just because of your one advice I had my
Harvard uh uh OPM uh batch this year I
not went there and I saved a lot of
money to paying them because I'm
learning more on AI while listening you
guys. Um so my question to you is uh Sim
and Dave how I shall take this uh step
forward where my my company in
Pertham.AI AI and we building this
agentic layer where the small
enterprises can work intelligently on
that and without any expensive softwares
and ERP and such and be competitive
where the transaction cost just just to
tell you the transaction cost of this
industry is 10 to 20% of sales here in
this part of the world which is 5 to 10x
of the profitability that industry make.
So that is the kind of inefficiency we
are talking and my MTP is because
millions of workers works in labor
industry in that part and we have to
save that and for saving that we have to
make sure the white collar process
should be the agentic so that the
efficiency keep continue. Yeah, I'm so
so glad you asked that question because
I I see this a lot. You know, people who
are in industries where you like, you
know, manufacturing is considered to be
very labor intensive. But when you look
at the actual operating costs of the
company, it's all about planning
transactions, documents, all of which is
beautiful AI territory. And then you
look at the numbers and you're like,
"Wow, we could we could drop 10, 20, 30%
more to the bottom line with stuff that
AI can do right now." And everyone's
thinking, "Oh, but first I would need
to, you know, have robots all over the
place." Like, no, no, no, no. Do it just
with the paperwork and the planning and
the scheduling and the the inefficiency
of where people are and what they're
doing. All of that is perfectly
attackable with AI. So, if you
productize that, you know, across a
region for, you know, a certain class of
companies, that should work incredibly
well. It's a it's a very, very cool
idea. One other meta topic is uh
everybody thinks all wealth and power is
going to go to like two or three places
in the world. But if you look at the
regulatory environments in those places
including the US, including California,
a lot of things are going to be very
very slow because of regulatory
slowdowns and there are many places in
the world that can move much more
quickly. So if you can identify the
subsets that sure it could happen in
China, sure it could happen in the US
but it won't because of this government
blocking action. This happens a ton in
biotech. It it'll come in self-driving.
It'll come in drones, you know, the
flying drones, drone delivery. All of
those areas will deploy in other areas
of the world much more quickly than the
US because of regulatory slowdown. you
know, get those deployed there, uh,
wherever they can take off and flourish
and then they can backport to the US.
That's always been a really good
business plan.
Sim, anything you want to add to that?
Are you transacting some huge Bangalore
deal?
>> I'm trans I'm just trying to get my way
through this city, so I'll I'll beg off
on this particular one.
>> Can you Can you point the camera out the
window? I really want to see some uh see
some media here.
>> Okay, hold on.
Um, this is a Bangalore at night and all
you see is construction. Can you see
some of that?
>> Or how about at the front where there's
a ton of trans there's a ton of traffic.
>> Okay. Let's go to to uh RA.
>> Not the tour. Not the tour I was looking
for, but that was all right.
>> All right. Well, thank you. Listen, this
is a greeting from from from Germany and
uh speaking David in your language. I
listen to a lot of podcasts,
international, national ones. You're 10x
the best in the world. You know, I
follow you for years. This this is for
sure. It's it's it's arising like pop
stars. It's it's amazing. Um my question
is um I think in the last couple of
editions we see an increase concern on
on security. Of course, I think we
captured it captured it here a number of
times and and then I think Alex you
framed it a little a few weeks ago as
potentially a marketing thing because
all the CEOs have a have a commercial
interest in all of that. Now we see more
and more the Hintons of the world, the
Hararis, the Gavdats and other
scientists warn as well in a certain
way. So far so good. I mean it's
technology. We need to we need to
somehow manage it to to to find right
answers maybe on a scale never as we've
seen never before. What triggers me most
at the moment and this is US and Europe
equally the same. It's the public
opinion on AI and this is predominantly
driven by the media, right? everything
which is bad, which is a little poor,
which is scary, which is whatever, the
media jumps on it and have a headline,
you know, and and I can tell you here
it's it's even worse than everywhere
else. It's and versus, you know,
Singapore for instance, right? Or other
company, other countries adopting it
much more. And and how do you how do you
treat that? Because I I mean, you're on
this path of optimism like we all are,
right? And and I do this also as part of
Accenture, part of my job every day. Um,
and it's exciting. I feel I feel 10
times accelerated as a human being since
I deal with that. But the media
doomerism, so to say, is so
counterproductive. And yes, we have
challenges, of course, we all need to
work on those. What's what's your
opinion? I know you try hard, but I
mean, what do you think?
>> So, the media is is always going to be
broken from here forward because they're
starved for money. they have no budget
and so they have to chase drama in order
to even survive and so that you just got
to write off the mainstream media. I
think the the c the antidote to that is
uh micro media or you know X and
podcasts and you know narrowcasting and
I I think in particular Germany to me is
the most talented place on the planet
that isn't doing AI. It's just
mind-blowing. And I I keep running into
people in California that have come over
from Germany and I I'm like you're in
the right place. What you want to do is
go to PaloAlto, go to San Francisco,
spend a month, pick up the culture, go
in a group of like five or seven people,
and then backport it, bring it back to
Germany and expand it, but do it with
like seven becomes 50 becomes 500 people
that are all communicating through
podcasts and through X and through Slack
and through texting that, you know, they
realize that everyone around them is
completely out of touch with what's
going on. And that's okay because within
that group they're self-reinforcing. You
just need to get those critical masses
of people. So I think the antidote to
main mainstream media is narrowcasted
media and it just kind of it percolates
on its own.
>> Yeah. I just wanted to jump in there
because at the end of the day what you
let into your mind is critical, right?
uh you know having some uh you know news
producer decide what you learn or some
editor decide what you read um I would I
I don't give them that option. I'm very
careful like what I put into my body
from a food perspective and what I let
into my mind from a shaping my neural
net perspective and I choose very
carefully the content that I absorb and
you guys are doing that as well. you're,
you know, listening listening to the
podcast. So, uh, that's just it. Uh,
Alex or Sim, you want to add to that?
>> I, I'll just note maybe the the obvious
point, you could always leave Europe.
Europe has been hobbled both due to
external factors and internal factors.
the the postcold war era and there are a
number of historians who've written in
particular about the role that the
George HW Bush administration at the end
of the cold war played in uh deciding
whether Europe would be brought more
even more into the US orbit postcold war
versus forming a stronger federation
like EU and the bias was bring Europe
into more of a US orbit so that it would
be less independent
That may or may not have been the right
geopolitical decision at the time. But I
think now what we're seeing is a Europe
that's energy hobbled, that's
politically in certain ways hobbled,
that doesn't enjoy uh this is again
widely reported uh certain freedoms uh
of speech and action that are considered
fundamental in the US. But I I think it
really it's energy uh energy policy and
associated policies that have left
Europe hobbled. And so then if if you're
really interested in accelerationism and
you're Europe, what do you do? Well,
either you get your energy act together
so that you can afford to power your own
data centers or you leave. And I I think
this is the question. And and by the
way, this has to happen on a relatively
abbreviated time scale because we're in
in the middle of recursive
self-improvement. So anyone who who
wants to play top-notch ball in the
infrastructure game in Europe has to be
asking the question right now. Either
solve the energy plus data center crunch
together with the the conccomant policy
issues or just move to hopefully the the
US block the pox silica and do it here.
>> Yeah. One of my good friends, Guy
Bradley, actually, he's he's actually
British, but he he came to the US, made
a fortune uh in tech in the US, and then
moved back to Germany. He speaks perfect
German and French. So, he has a place in
southern France and a place in Germany.
And he there's no better place on the
planet to live in his opinion, and I
agree actually uh between between
Germany and France. It's just
beautifully protected from everything
that's damaging in the world. and and
you look at other jurisdictions, you
know, that uh you know, like India, for
example, where it's just rampant growth,
but it's absolutely trashed. And it's
like so so I think I'm I'm always
surprised that more Germans are not in
Boston and Silicon Valley. I think
there's a lot of national pride, but if
you just do a 5-year tour of duty in the
US, you're going to be so overwhelmingly
happy when you move back to uh to
Germany. It really it really feels like
it should happen more. I I I can tell
you I'm an international traveler,
Seline. 21 times I was in Bangalore. So
I see all this rising and I wonder,
Alex, absolutely. What are we doing over
here? Why do we don't why don't we wake
up? Why are we under whatever kind of
avenue? But anyway, that's that's
another topic. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, Rafe. Over to you, Ron.
>> And we'll go for another 10 minutes and
then we're going to have to jump into
our normal days here.
>> Okay. Um, thanks so much for doing this.
I'm calling in from uh Calgary, Canada
and longtime listener and uh I'm a
screenwriter director. So uh a big
special thank you to Peter because uh I
was in a bad place uh when I was uh in
the early uh early this year I was
writing something about China and uh
yeah I was like borderline depressed but
uh since I've been uh uh you know
writing uh another project for uh future
vision uh you know x-prise you know I
have become a bit more optimistic about
the future and everything. I also read
the books uh Peter wrote the abundance
and uh you know we are as gods and u so
I've been thinking so since uh
everything is uh hooked or incinerated
as Alex would say uh what is the like
one of the hardest problem still left so
I kept coming back to like distrust
between rival nations right and uh I
read solve everything two weeks ago and
Alex and Peter you actually described
agreement as one of the new scarcities
uh once cognition becomes abundant.
Right? So I wonder could agreement under
distrust itself become computebound and
could coordination between rivals like
the US and China uh become an
engineering problem. So here's my
question. uh as sovereign AIS will
increasingly advise governments who we
create a shared protocol uh that they
can connect to and use AI and privacy
preserving computation to search for
improving agreements without either side
exposing uh protected data. Um is that
technically an institutionally
meaningful direction and if it is you
know what do each of you think is the
hardest part uh we should solve first?
Thank you
>> Alex. Over to you, pal.
>> Yeah. Um, so I'll give you a hot take
because that's what people want, I
think. Uh, so multi multi-party
computing, MPC or distributed
multi-party, uh, computation is a very
fashionable problem in computer science
right now. Enabling enabling multiple
parties in a zero trust way to
collaborate, to share data, to achieve
convergence, to mediate, very
fashionable. However,
my hot take on this one is I don't think
that's the limiting factor for say
international peace. If if if you said
the the goal is I I want uh I I don't
want a second cold war between the US
and China. I uh I I want you know world
peace uh thousand years of peace or
whatever it looks like. I don't actually
think that the solution looks
algorithmic in nature. It probably looks
more geopolitical infrastructural like
solve the Taiwan issue and redmesticate
all supply chains everywhere to every
country so that the the international
trade in physical products can afford to
be cut off without a global depression.
I I think what we've seen even just in
the recent years in the Middle East is
in no small part because America can now
frack its way and has fracked its way to
fossil fuel energy sovereignty and
independence. And I I want to generalize
that example which I think is very
instructive to what happens when the US
no longer needs China or Taiwan or South
Korea or Japan for any advanced
manufacturing at all. I think it would
be a very different world. So in
summary, if the goal is world peace,
obliterate, as perverse as this sounds,
obliterate, cook, incinerate the need
for global trade in products and
services. And perversely, I think you
get a very peaceful world. And I don't
think there's an algorithmic component
to that. Not to first order.
>> Yeah, Peter,
>> I got I got I got oil on my hands. I
couldn't get any on me.
>> Peter, this is your cooking show. We're
doing the cooking show. Oh, that's cool.
Yeah, let's see what you're what you're
doing there.
>> I'm sure it's healthy. Whatever it is,
>> it it is it is. It's an omelette for my
boys. Uh Anthony, over to you.
>> Yes. Hello to the moonshot mates. Um I
want to thank you all for your time and
for the opportunity to participate in
the AMA.
Also, the podcast has been very valuable
uh especially in the time we're in where
people are looking at it cynically and
negatives. You guys have been a hope and
optimism for me. Uh just a simple
question
is what books or material do you
recommend reading to prepare for the
transition we're in? I know you've
mentioned Diamond Age and uh Ray's
books, The Singularity and um some other
works he has. I was just curious if you
had any other material that you think is
important to read. Uh, Alex, what's your
>> Yeah, I'll I'll comment and this is
probably the last question I can take
before I need to drop. Read Solve
Everything as folks in the comments. So,
solveverthing.org, which Peter and I
wrote. And then if you like sci-fi, read
Accelerondo by Charlie St, which is I
think the the single best sci-fi
treatment of what's what we're what's in
the process of happening right now.
>> So, everybody, listen, thank you for
joining us. Uh, we love this, you know,
the last one and this one. We're going
to do this again. Uh it's a chance for
us to really connect with everybody,
hear your thoughts. Um we have such
brilliant minds with Alex and Seem and
Dave. Uh I feel grateful to spend time
with them every week and spend time with
you. You know, we know your time is your
most precious thing. So we appreciate
it. Um remember you can join Moonshots
Live now by uh by uh on the live stream.
Uh so if you're not able to make it in
person and we and please it's going to
be an amazing event. join us on the live
stream and uh we're grateful for your
time. Everybody have a beautiful day and
see you all again very soon.